Guide to the Sir Leslie Stephen Papers, 1861-1959 (bulk 1866-1891)
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Sir Leslie Stephen papers 1861-1959 (bulk 1866-1891)
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Stephen, Leslie, Sir, 1832-1904.
1.0 linear feet Extent: 298 Items
British author, philosopher, and first editor of the Dictionary of National Biography. Chiefly correspondence between Stephen and his first wife, Harriet Marian ("Minny") Thackeray, daughter of William Makepeace Thackeray, during their courtship and marriage. Several letters written to family members during the Stephen's honeymoon and later sojourns in Switzeralnd were illustrated with drawings by both. Includes letters from other relatives and letters of condolence at Minny's death. In a few letters to his second wife, Julia Duckworth Stephen, Stephen mentions their children "Nessa and Ginia" (Vanessa Bell and Virginia Woolf). Five letters from Stephen to Sir Henry John Newbolt concern Newbolt's poetry. Includes 21 manuscript articles written by Stephen for CORNHILL MAGAZINE while Thackeray was editor. Also contains a small number of printed articles and a reproduction of Stephen's portrait by G. F. Watts.
RL.01260
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Sir Leslie Stephen Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1964.
Biographical Note
British author, philosopher, and first editor of the Dictionary of National Biography.
Collection Overview
Chiefly family correspondence and manuscripts of articles by Sir Leslie Stephen (1832-1904), author, philosopher, and first editor of the Dictionary of National Biography. Included are the letters of his first wife, Harriet Marian (Thackeray) Stephen, daughter of William Makepeace Thackeray, and of his second wife, Julia Prinsep (Jackson) Duckworth Stephen, whose children included Virginia Woolf and Vanessa Bell. Correspondence discusses visits to Cambridge, England, by Stephen in 1866, and 1869; almost yearly tours of Switzerland, especially the Alps, by Sir Leslie and Harriet Marian (Thackeray) Stephen after their marriage in 1867 until her death in 1875; a tour of America in 1868, where they met James Russell Lowell, Oliver Wendell Holmes, Ralph Waldo Emerson, Charles Sumner, and Elizabeth H. Putnam; meetings with George Otto Trevelyan, Henry Fawcett, Matthew Arnold, William Ernest Henley, and Alfred Tennyson; Stephen's opinion of a novel by Millicent Fawcett; and Stephen's biography of Henry Fawcett, the proceeds from his writings, and his work on the Dictionary of National Biography. Also included are a poem by Sir Henry Taylor written in 1864; report, 1895, of a committee for the establishment of a memorial to Thomas Henry Huxley; clipping, 1898, of a congratulatory letter to George Meredith on his seventieth birthday, with a note on Meredith by Stephen; report, 1900, concerning a memorial for Henry Sidgwick; several pages from the Proceedings of the Alpine Club, 1899, relating to the election of James Bryce as president, pages from The Cambridge Review, 1900, containing statements about James Porter, former master of St. Peter's College, Cambridge; proofs or printed copies of eight of Stephen's magazine articles; and twentyone manuscripts of articles by Stephen.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Authors -- Biography -- Sources; Authors, British; English literature -- 19th century; Switzerland -- Description and travel; Voyages and travel; Stephen, H. Marion (Harriet Marion), 1823-1858; Stephen, Julia Duckworth, 1846-1895
Contents of Collection
- Container List
  - Correspondence, 1861-1866 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1867
  - Correspondence, 1868-1869
  - Correspondence, 1870
  - Correspondence, 1871-1872
  - Correspondence, 1873-1874
  - Correspondence, 1875
  - Correspondence, 1876-1959, undated
  - Printed Material, 1892-1966, undated
  - Pictures
  - Manuscript Articles - Author's Introductory Note (Box 2)
  - Manuscript Article: Another View
  - Manuscript Article: A Cynic's Apology
  - Manuscript Article: Useless Knowledge
  - Manuscript Article: The Decay of Murder
  - Manuscript Article: Heroes and Valets
  - Manuscript Article: Idolatry
  - Manuscript Article: The Late Lord Lytton as a Novelist
  - Manuscript Article: National Antipathies
  - Manuscript Article: Oratory
  - Manuscript Article: Our Rulers
  - Manuscript Article: Senior Wranglers
  - Manuscript Article: Social Slavery
  - Manuscript Article: Literary Exhaustion
  - Manuscript Article: The Decay of Literature
  - Manuscript Article: Thoughts of an Outsider: Public Schools
  - Manuscript Article: Thoughts of an Outsider: Public Schools Again
  - Manuscript Article: The Uses of Fools
  - Manuscript Article: The Study of English Literature
  - Manuscript Article: Seventy-Six
  - Manuscript Article: Untitled
  - Manuscript Article: Vacations